Good afternoon well, hooters talk my name's mark...I'm a program manager works on the
...service fabric team hi I'm google more the mone of engineering managers on the service
fabricating so today we're going to talk to-you about how you can build a
scalable resilient services using the program model apis
...tobin encourage you to download and su cui that we ship this week
use sdk and you'll see it into this talking
...build yourself the same scalable applications will show but plenty demos here today.
I'm going to touch a little bit on the benefits of why we build service fabric
is a platform has been the vast majority of time thinking about how we builders applications and
...inside visual studio and show you code we...the rise per program moles we have
...imitators applications...how you can simply scalable out.
If any of you attended a gopal...told yesterday
gave great run-down of why we built a platform for buildingservices that we
...microsoft here leisure we've always been focused on building a platform itself, you know, when we first...a
...on building this concept of work rules and web rules could we realize that building...role the m
is just hard, you know, you can't just build...your machine fails what was running on it how do I
fail it all over...of my service so you
build services you need a platform to take that hard work away from you and we're microsoft
have been doing exactly the same transition for a number of years we've taken a lot of box products we built before
sequel...a system center your ling...sky for business and we've been hosting them...services...the
cloud we realized we did that we had to build a new platform...with thrills
we'll say that after many years of development we've actually kind of get this platform...think this is...next generation of
has a platform...giving you we used to build and run our own services on
...reasons why we have to do this and the most important came across as we building services we realized we had the
breakdown...applications into the concept of micros services pieces of code that
...independently deployable version of all...had unique names and
regrettable and here let's take...reasons why?
The first and foremost...when you build...service scalers unpredictable you might sort of...machines you might get to
thirty...might go to three hundred machines you don't...to build re architecture app constantly because of the
scaled...for they...scale down.
You secondly...concept of agility we...years of
...engineering team building a big box product we ship that every few years in all engineers are
focused on that as you run a service...become much more agile...how
to fundamental changes id engineering teams at microsoft sql leisure teams,
for example, change from focusing on bookwork features for
develop style they run a service now and not meant they had to...individual
teams...to ship...deploy individual pieces at different times so,
for example, when you see collages a team ability database microsoft as a...the
...the protocol gateway services team that...the backup and restore...
and each one of them has...and their own scheduler their own time frame they couldn't wait for each other
there's a lot more agility and getting their things rolled out new functionality fixing bugs
and each one of those had...across a set of machines had...versioning the deployment and the
...all those mexico's came resilience...important
...have when you're running a scales of machine running hundred machines what
a single machine fails you can't just simply go what was on that machine hardware...machine how do I
...the services running inside the machine you have to be able to deal with automatic fail over
...do a self healing of the service itself...say a little machine fail I just
when you service fabric the underlying platform to take care or making sure that those
serves it redistribute against the remaining soda machines at
run then of course came cost if you look at the cloud services today...
up five work...you...been...m and placement process...why can't I just run,
you know,
all these different work roles on the same, you know, smaller number...well this is exactly will service fabric does
we break things down is micros services and we can deploy hundreds of micros services
onto a small set of the m...sort of three and go-to...to three hundred so we can packing
densities and helps reduce costs when you start to run these services a scale...becomes
a very important factor so all of this drove us to build a platform we uses
...services the bits that we gave out yesterday exactly the same bits that we run inside out
datacenters in fact we just cut the for release what we should...few days
...actual for releases still being rolled out inside offers...services
...get before and what teams of deployed we sort of frills...say that when you take this and deployed on your
machines...the same code that we use inside...services
and even more so our objective is that we're taking this platform...only will you builds
a take...applications that you...against this sdk and...service...run inside as
your but...putting the same platform directly...windows...twenty sixteen
what that means is that you build...applications you can...insider
...with no code changes...cluster machines on windows server and you can...your private clouds
you...anywhere by windows have a twenty sixties running of course beyond that
we're also looking how we pull the whole platform with a linux and...on a of
os of your choice so now you...say to choose the always have your choice and you build a
played to the location of your choice of course the whole platform is designed
...you feasibility apis we provide...bring your own runtime about how you
...as well as incredibly flexible and we're very excited
...say this is the way that we think about how you should build scalable resilient applications?
So, let me get just a few concepts and place because understanding a few of these concepts
object really appreciate and understand the demos that we're going to run through.
...we talk about a cluster what this does is we take a set of machines physical
machines or...m and we stitching together from a cluster machines and this cluster can
be scalable from three had machines to xxx machines to three hundred machines kind of interface get
...scale-up and can scale it out consists of machines of different sizes
...because you can think of this is a collection as a whole?
What happens then is that you come along and you define and build an application that consists
of micros services pieces of code that you can decomposing your applications using very
much about design in terms of components ionization of your application what happens
then...application which is sort of a logical collection of these services you bill many of them
and you simply say to service fabric deploy this application into the...containing microwaves
...distribute across the set of cluster machines in most efficient
way we understand resources of the actual micros service that uses
...resources of the machines we just moved to the most efficient placement around all that?
Of course what can happen typically you deploys micros services...machines
...we're all about resilience and failure and it's a thing to have in a distributed system,
you know, there are machines that will die you...visibility of having canonicalization of hardware
...have cheap commercialization of hardware where you have one of know
...failures are not going to bring down your service will
invested case we simply go how we understand exactly what was running that we knew exactly the microsoft
as with that whether we simply look how we redistribute them around the remaining set of
...machines inside the cluster as far as you're concerned or this transparent
...make sure they have constant high availability resilience in your service this is how
we build large-scale mission critical services that we run on like sequel
...databases document db event hubs in...here this
is a critical part of how we make sure that there's a full resilience inside a
...of...clusters well can span multiple datacenters or multiple regions
...provide resilience beyond the bounds all of, you know, just a singleand,
region itself and in fact if you take one of...services we run which is the back-end of
...they spread out across three different being datacenters...they run this.
So, given a little bit
of background about the concepts let's talk about what you can actually build what we do is
we split applications into typically to types we talk about stateless services we talk about
stateful services stainless ones are something that you're...almost exactly familiar with today
...of the things like cloud services...worker roles isp dot net applications
...gets external...is some stole with us as your storage all
sequel databases and typically when not piece of code starts...a positive from the
store and does is computation on it and if that particular service goes down...instantiated
somewhere else...data...one of the great innovations...enormous innovation we have a
force to build was concept of stateful services and stateful services have
to huge benefits one is that...reduce latency?
What that means is when request coming from your client the state...your code
...co-located together we take the state of your application the data
...it highly resilience by a persisting at low clear making replica copies of it scenario
compute and state...co-located together that reduces
latency enormously so you don't have to go to some back...back secondly and critically is a
...service actually reduce the complexity replication when you start to think about stateful
services a starting about designs today I'm almost certain that you built applications
and services today request comes in from a client it goes into a q you pull it out from the
q and you put into your work role and then from that work role impressions some
...install and it's really pretty have some caches...improve the related...back
...well one of the key aspects of stateful services is what we've effect redone we've democratizing
okay we've given high availability to all of you as part of probing model a simple
...or that means now is you can get rid of those externalities...and get rid of those
x analyze caches because your application is naturally highly resilience you don't need to have a q
...your application is naturally a cache the dangers simply the data
...is made resilience and replicated across a set of...already...in the middle
tier you run your code so deeply simplifies how we do these things
an example a back-end of kona where you run ...across
...set of cluster...machines they built a stateful service that gives run
...about a thousand instances or more of the microsoft they run and
...as a query engine...does it has a number of subscriptions
runs link queries across incoming data feeds so lots and lots of data is coming
from the traffic is coming from finance coming from whether they
have huge numbers of the microsoft is run they have a query expression they evaluate
billionsmillions of these query expressions across a partition set of services
and any time there's a failure one of those machines always query expressions
...across another to another services running as you get very fast fail
...this example of the stateful
less they have fast fail over where they can actually do query expressions
...incoming data and when they hit...career expressions,
for example,...your gps location and tell me whether the traffic alert they
...visual notification if they...to build-out as a stateless service putting a lot data
...running always rules...eventu the failure the failure...subscriptions would give you a
...slow experience for you to be a have a
...responsive time in terms of making sure you
have notifications about what happens and finally we provides runtime that allows you to build status
and stateful services but of course we can to completely embrace any other runtime you want to
deploy in terms of what we call a micros service with you some
new js or whether you use an arbitrary axial deploy that will make it free resilient
...copies of it running and one of the machines failed will make sure that always running somewhere so you can bring your own
run...combine that with our runtime and typically what
we find is that many applications consists of some statefull some
stinger services and different runtime in all this compose together and
manage as a single entity a across the service fabric?
So, how is it you can...some of these things so effectively have to
...model apis one that we call reliable actors and one of recall reliable
services and both of them take advantage of the full platform capabilities
and using either...api you can build micros services and be able
to compose replications from those and typically we find that many application we have
compose from both...models in terms of how they...this whichever you choose
...of the full platform underneath it all trying to do is
...of ripple he's going to talk us through but some of the launches warning means by access
...so everyone so...reliable
...basically allows you to...hardness the full our of service fabric by
using very simple programming modeler to virtual activist programming model
it suitable for like coyote or games where you can actually divide
your state as well as logic into very small independent units and they can all run and,
run in parallel the runtime provides you basically automatic state management
as well as it provides a very simple...concurrency what it means that you
don't have to write complicated synchronization logic you do not have to write complicated
...to save your state to some back-end database and make
it reliable the platform takes care of takes care of that for-you so,
now let's go ahead then and look at building
...reliable actor we'll start with stateless reliable actor and then we'll go and make it make
the state more reliable so I'm going to switch over to visual studio?
So, you notice in...we have done a full integration with visual studio of a new
create a new project you'll see the templates which are basically you can create services using
...you can create services using the...allowable services programming model so,
here I already created a project we're using this
template which is the stateless active service in this case my actor is
a so there are there are three things that you need to do in order to build a reliable actor
...you define the interface...just like objects so,
you define an interface in this case I'm defining a counteract
interface it obviously has a certain method in order to set the...
and get method to get the...or more appropriate set method which is a compare
an exchange method right so that's the first thing that you do the second thing is that
we have to go and implement...so, you go ahead and implement the counterso,
in this caseI'm implementing the count of the value
...stored in a member variable so you derived from an actor and then you implement
your actor interface and the compare exchanges doing a normal compare
exchange...look at this course in this scored we have not
written any synchronization logic we have not written any management
state management logic activation logic nothing of that sort right so very simple
...it's like any other any of the plastic you would write.
The third thing that you need to do is to basically register the actor
with the runtime so that runtime can activated as needed so,
here I create a fabric runtime...just...the actor which is my actor and,
I rate for the activation stew to happen so,
let's go ahead and are deployed this active solution into
...actor application into one of the local cluster that we how you'll see that so,
while it is deploying let's go ahead and look at how would you actually use the actor
in order to use the actor you connect to it through what we call an actor
...proxy provides location transparency it allows you to
identify the actor using the actor id and, you can identify
that...either through all a string identifier all you can use
along or you can use a good so,
you say I want to connect to account director in this case counter one and,
you create a proxy to it so,
now the active roxy will provide location transparency you will connect to the right
...will dispatcher method if let's say that...to fail
and the runtime were to re instantiated somewhere else it will transparently reconnect
and your calls will go through you would not have to handle any fail over logic whatsoever so,
in this case what I'm doing is that ...just get the counter
value current counter value and then I increment the counter value by adding
one-two it right now let's see what is deployed in
the cluster so this is my local cluster it's running on this laptop it's running
find nodes on this laptop and it's running the exactly the same
...as it would run in the datacenter...there is no difference this is one of
theone of the big difference with respect to the previous cloud services
vibration and this whereas up in the previous cloud services
that was an emulator here there is no emulator it is exactly the same core so
if you record runs on your machine you know,
that yes it will actually run in the production environment as well?
So, I have final cluster let's see the application is deplore this is a counter
application.
And, it contains one count of service so,
here is here is the application of this is the service it
has one partition...right and that partition is running on node
four right so let's go ahead look at on nor for.
What is running for node for you can see that we have over counter
...running on node four?
And, it has one instance placed in that knownso,
now I'm going to go back and run the client.
So, the client disconnected to the actor through that roxy as we saw in the
...basically incrementing the counter right.
So,...I'm going to put this to refresh.
So, you see what happens the counter is actually on node
...go ahead and
...the...on...four.
You saw that the system to fill overreaction.
That...transparently reconnected the client
...another instantiation of the actor and.
Well, we lost our work on so we lost
...stared which was which was expected because we were storing the
...in a member variable right so we made
...reliable...but we didn't make the state reliableso,
let's go ahead and look at how can we make this state more reliable right?
...stalled the client.
...exactly example of...we got from a state disservice...failure and recover
...recovered my state fromeither from the beginning because the computational because I pulled from some
...lifestyle right so I'll go back to over counteract implementation so,
in order to make ...stateful reliable actor you need to define the
state you can define any state that is utilize herbal so,
in this case of define account
...which contains value for the counter now rather than deriving from the
actor of actor you will derive from actor of the...in this case it's count of state.
Right now that we have derived from
...from a stateful actor we do not need to store the member variables so...common
this out now I need to get this value.
From a base state property.
This property is the reliable state so when an
actor is instantiated we hydrated this property with the
last consistent value if you make changes to this property when your method returns
it automatically get saved so this is the automatic state management that I
was talking about so let me go ahead and modify all of this scored.
So, what you'll see in the beauty of all of this is now the states contained
is a stateful service and...do the failure again use
...completely different experience right so again as you saw that I
did not write any synchronization logic here that...on currencies providing
what provided by the runtime is taking care of the synchronization for
...so whenever any of these methods are in progress is guaranteed that
...method is being called so you can make changes to your state are just like as you would in
...normal dot net class without worrying about concurrency
and once so in the search method when we said the value of
the state ones the method returns the state will be replicated...and replica
...and, quorum committed so let's go ahead deploy
...solution again...employment times here...seconds
to deploy your service now as opposed to cloud services today...a few seconds...and running
and...are services deployed of a great benefits as well we have of this platform?
Actually I wanted to do one more thing from...be deployed again grange.
...to fly all the time I mean...to put a break point here ensure
that you've already integrated debugging capabilities in the platform as well
so while I deploy the bit's actually gone to those local cluster
the process gets activated and the visual studio can next to that
...that and attaches...and gives you the complete debugging experience so,
I'll go back and go to the clientele he'll hit that point.
Super-fast deployment time.
And,...point is head of the client is saying that I want to set of value of one and the
previous value was zero which was true because we just activated this actor
...again, you know, that the client actually does this in a loop so it will come back and
it will say hey why don't you said the value to the previous value was one
someone remove the break point...this goal detest the debug...
as you can see the client is going it's incrementing the value so let's go back to the
service public explorer and see what got deployed some refreshed this.
So, this time you'll notice that I have one partition but I actually have three
...I have a primary and then...these so,
as the state changes are done on a primary they get replicated onto
the second is right so.
That's exactly how you make a...stateful services we have copies
...state replicated around you kill machines, you know,
exactly where they are never lose anybody data...sequel leisure databases is
book exactly like...copies of databases machine fails we just fail over the other
copy...so you known what I'm going to do next I'm going to actually
restart this primary the notice what happens in this area?
As a...what happens as well as to the client.
So, you can see a replica went down immediately another replica
was selected as a primary and, then you can see here.
That we did not lose overstate...started from the same state right...
So, that's how easy it is to build
...reliable stateful services using actor programming model
let's switch back to so that a lot of features in the
actor programming model that we when shown we have.
...session that you can goal and what's so that we can
...to actually talking about the reliable services programming model so,
please go to this session and then watch it...whenever you
can if we talk aboutindepth all the feature that the reliable
actor api provides so back to...so let's talk a little bit about what you saw and...
build on another concept here about how we package deploy and instantiate these applications
...to understand how the...is very important and how you think about...says
...you think about writing some code to be also has some configuration associated
with you...that coding configuration you...together you put that into what we call
the service package the package as a manifests...representation of it
is represents a unit of deployment okay and this think of this think this is simply as
a...type what you do next you...define
...application package...package is like a
container for the service packages it defines of boundary versioning
...boundaries isolation find bunches of lifetime of it
...itself then you can take and you put your service packages
inside here I can define a service package full...service I've had
...I can come along and define another service package here and this might be a web application and this
will be called the uk ...web application type so I've got two types of services
deployment side my application package which provides logical boundary around
...gives units...lifetime versioning and isolation nothing itself is defined as a type?
So, what do I do...
I do now is have defined these types I...load them into
a service fabric we have inside a service called image so what we define only...
always package types and what you can do now you come along and take these package types
...going to create instances of them so remember what's of
...straightforward a service-type is like aasl type and application
packages a contain a for multiple those service types and now just as you think in tabs of
object orientation mechanism we...instances of these things so I can create an instance of
application type and inside that instance of application type
...instances of the service-type to the contains so I gave my cluster
and here this point in time I sang a create and instance and every application instance has a name
associated with it so in this case it may have a namesake fabric slash
...replication and then when I say to service fabric I want
you to deploy the contains service-type and trick instances of those
...from those instances of those micros services have a unique name associated with them,
for example, here are deployed one of the counter service types the other one is
the account a web application type we create instances of those
that associated with that particular application package instance
...results you can have the same way using about types inside
...create hundreds of instances of a particular application
type of a particular versioning I can upgrade and the downgrade any particular
one of those of the set of instances...with that type so this is how we think about
defining microsoft's packaging it and deploying...creating instances
...so we're...going to look at the next program model api I'm going to get...to
...dive into the benefits of housing about reliable services so we looked at the
actor apis it-was property simple to build
stateful and stateless services now if you need
more control and more flexibility you want to use reliable services api
you also can build a very powerful stateless and, stateful applications so,
for example, let's say if you're using
...existing isbn...app you can hosted as a stateless application insights
that was fabric using reliable services api you can also
be powerful stateful applications using reliable collection which we'll talk in
...in a bit so,
in the actor apis we talked about how there was a
...based on currency and then any changes that you make...to your state
...saved at the end of the method well, for the allowable collection
api a sorry reliable services api using the reliable collection api
will give you more control in terms of managing the concurrency as well
as the granularity of your of your update so you can actually have
multiple simultaneous updates happening
to independent keys at the same time and you can out to...throughput applications you
can also communicate using the technology of your choice so, for example,
for the acted apis we were using...proxy and,
we did not know what transported was using
it just independently provided a connection between connection to over to
...for the reliable services api you can use w cf you can
use web api all you can use what we call the service...just like active
proxy or any other any other protocols you may how you can use
...socket the cp
...ftp whatever you preferred...provides more flexibility in terms of communication?
Now building stateful services is really,
really hard and getting...correct is really hard so, what we are doing is that we
...providing you the same familiar concepts that you have
known for your in order to build the your applications using dot
net so previously used to build applications on a single machine single threaded using dot
net collection we then started using...connection collections in order to
provide multi-threaded access we now so you think of
reliably collection as a natural evolution to that it's a collection that basically
spans multi much...machine it offered search it it's...and,
it's transactional?
So, what are the to other to reliably collections that we offer out-of-the-box
so you can use reliable dictionary of key and value or you can use reliable
...you cannot atomically updated one or more of these collections
so you can instantiateone reliable dictionary inside your service or ten reliable
...you can you can instantiate one q fight you are fight you than and
file five...it's up to you and, you can anatomically update
this collections using transactions unsold the transactions
...those reliably collections the changes that you make our replicated and
the arguably...store on multiple replicas within within the cluster the
...when you are of within the transaction the...are reputable and,
the new mutations when you when you enumerate this
...they give you a consistent snapshot of what is
there in the collection so now let's go ahead and build reliable service so,
this time...build award...service all switch over to visual studio?
...build a simple word...service which.
You can add awards to it as the words are added
...counting the occurrences of those words and it is
also counting the total number of words that it has seen so far and,
this get cone dissing method basically returns what is the total count of the words that have been
process you'll notice here I'm using w cf this is the
wc of contract in order to connect to the service and then add the words or
get the cones we'll see other form of communication as we go along and in the
...so here is the stateless service I
derive the stateless service from my work on stateless service from a stateless service
I implement the work on service
interfacehere this is a stateless service so I'm I naturally want multiple
...access...going to use gone current collections
...as I'm using a conquering q in order to the as an input
...as the words that I'll put the words into the...so if you look at the ad
...implementation you'll see that as awards arrive there just include into the
q right then I have a dictionary that basically keeps the
count of those...those words and,
then I have another dictionary that basically contains the total number of
words process through a key which is total...process...I could have
use actually just a member variable here I'm using this to
schorr how you would map that when we build the stateful services so,
there are two things that happen when a services instantiated by service public
...we gordon
...the service...give me your communication listener and that communication
listener has very simple open close and abort method and open
return string this is the address on which your services listening for when
your client ask you hey I want to resolve this service you saw that the services
had names so when the client ascii I want to resolve this service this is the address that we provide to that
...so in this case I'm using
the wc of communication listener this is one of the type that we are
...as part of the reliable services api so,
there is nothing here that's extra you just do new wc of communication
let's not give your contract and say this is the class that implements?
The second thing that happens is that once the services ready...runny
...method is called think of this as the current run method in your in your work and
rule so this is where...doing most of your processing so in this one
method you'll notice the cancellation token here so this cancellation token
is rallied as long as this instance of the
chord is the one that is in the statefull
...primary or in the stateless case is the actual instance...that is handling the
request let's say...to a load balancing movement this instance get
move to a different...within the cluster of this cancellation token will be
canceled by the runtime and then you can react accordingly to save the cancellation token
is cancel I'm...doing the processing because another instance
...get started on a different north and the run erasing method of dot instance we'll get
...so I'm doing a simple dq here
...as long as the items are available in the q a...and,
then I'll count award in the dictionary and then I'll update the total number
of words process right so let's go ahead then and
deployed this service in the same cluster.
While the deployment is happening let's look at how do we use this service or how do we
connect to it in case of factor reconnected using actor proxy?
In this case of...a client
that client says here is the uri of the service and when avoid has
been added...I need to look of where this word is or what
partition is serving this word we'll talk about partitioning in
...in a moment right now the services single partition as we were seeing
even inductor...as well as in this case the services single partition and,
recreate what we call the service partition...this represents
a logical connection to my service correct and in this case,
you know, that we are using...so you're
...service partition client is deriving from a service partition client of the
cf and what...implementing...and get...
When ad method has been called it
...the base class he give me the actual physical...so the base
...gives in the physical channel and then it go-there and...advertising?
This was going to provide me we also have this...
communication system but there's also going to be the ability to talk through web apis credit so we'll.
See that in a...
So, here the service partition...which is provided as...also we use
default service partition resolve...this associated with this...
community communication factory is providing you the location transparency and the
caching of the channel and,
again, this comes as part of...part of the reliable services api so
I think the service should have been deployed by now let's go ahead and look at
...so we have...owned application deployed.
What...statefull...look at the statefull...so this is the stateless work on
service it has obviously a single partition and one instance that is running on node
one to so let's go ahead and fire up the client to it?
So, there's a beautiful console uri...you can see that it's just adding the
...and it's getting that cones...continuously so now.
Let's go back and I'm going to go ahead and.
...replica on restart the core package a node tools so here is the
...applications stateless service package this is the core.
Right.
...restart...
You'll see that the cohn stomp.
Right while it did start but obviously we lost the state because we
...storing the state into the concurrent dictionary not actually the reliable
collections right so this is what happens when you what so you made the
...reliable and, then we'll talking
about how do you make the state reliable right so jump back to the powerpoint presentation?
So, what did I what do I need to dual if I had this
application today index in the current cloud services how would I make it
actually reliable right so the first thing that I have to do is tool...input
...that we had which was the concurrent you I have to make it reliable so I'm going to use
...right and then in order...have to store the
...into...the cones that I'm doing for the
words into the measure table or some other more...table...right so,
this is what it would look like so what whatever is this on this
side this is what would look like if in the current architecture not with service fabrics with
service fabric you basically get a request from your
front-end and your back-end is a stateful micro services using this reliable collection which
are dictionary then q and they have multiple...replicas than
...basically making the state reliable right so you reduce...
a typical three-d...with the front then related year and a back-end to just
...and, your middle dear which is your business logic
...your state income and, compute as...mention is co-located together?
So, let's go back to visual studio.
So, I mean the point is you can build stateless...as...deploy those.
...stateful ones as well and take advantage of those so you may have some existing
code that you just simply want to be...I want to build deploy that in a...way and,
take advantage of that...can also take advantage of how improve on that
the design concept by using stateful this and that way...reduce the complexity
on particular pieces of code the run inside and as you say typically most applications...both
...stateless gateway front-ends and we see can for a lot of the business
...shopping...database likes sit microsoft's is built in terms of a
statefull microsoft in without stateful apis so this is the
...cone servicenow it's a
state full-service you'll notice here is that I'm deriving from I'm deriving from
a state full-service rather than a stateless service I'm still implementing the same I
work on service interface I have stem create communication less than
... method let's see what happens in...previously when the...we
...basically putting the item into the...that we had as a member variable
inside here you'll notice that are november variables here so what we do is that we go ahead
and ask the state manager that's in the base class which is a
reliable state manager to say hey I need an input qi needed reliable
q here is the name of the q which is the input q and the name can be
a string or it can be a uri and you can have multiple ones of those you just
...manager hey I won't get a reliable
...collections in this case I'm getting a...q once I get the reliable
...q and item intuit and commit the transaction so once the transaction is
committed this item is reliably present in the cluster
it's replicated to answer of replica...within the cluster?
And, then again for the communication...I'm using w cf
for the runny...method I have an input qi have award
cone dictionary in a...dictionary seamus previously but instead of a member variable and a
...current dictionary I
...asking the state manager to give me reliable dictionary and
...q right so this is the different this is how you would get
hold of your reliable collections that you want to use
...your within your service again until the cancellation is requested
I'm basically getting the items from the input q and if there is an input
q item I'm adding the
item into the dictionary counting if there was an already in existing item
I'm increasing the...and then I'm saying that the total number of
words process update that as wellcommit the transaction now
this is important all of these three updates that I'm doing I'm
...queuing and item...another collection another dictionary the modifying
...dictionary all of these
are atomic which means that if my process where to fill somewhere here the
item that was dq using this method is actually...
queued until the transaction is committed so, this is the guarantee that we
provide that you can modify multiple collection anatomically and update them
atomically that's a super important thing think about if you write code today and it fails.
Have to...recovery...failures inside that and here we providing transactional guarantees
around updates on those dictionaries to make sure that intellect commit happens provide
full consistency and transaction...roles get some...then fart of the
...connect to the stateful service you'll see the words are being added and they
are being countered let's go ahead and go to go to
a what application so here is a...word
...service right it has one partition and just like for
...stateful actor it has three replica...
a primary primary and secondary primaries en node three output this
an to refresh we'll go ahead and restart the primary
on node three let me move this down?
So, primary replicas been restarted on the replica became
became the primary and you can see that the...are going on and then we haven't lost any
...previously we lost account all the state is reliable the
...still functional while a primary...because that was a very phosphate
...another replica became the secondary became a primary and then I
was able to continue the operation was able to continue the operation because
...is a quorum base system...of three replica to replicas were available
...do this again just so that you can follow along this is...we told...you know,
we've democratize ha you just build apps you simple program
...apis will guarantee the each...availability of this you can...
processes you can take down machines we will always make sure there's a copy with inside the system,
you know, we challenge you to...fully attack this system this is exactly what we do all the time if
I, you know, ...full reliability and consistency of this is how
we rely on the providing full transactional stateful serves that
we run allele heavy workloads on today like sequel leisure and...db
...to restart the replica the replica is now on primaries on node for you'll
notice a switch over happening right here so this became primary that was an active secondary the
...out-going while this replica is still down and it's building software awhile
what will happen is that will start to build-up this replica of this replica will come up it will
...in build which means that while this replica is down that
as bunch of operations happening all of these operations the words that are being added
...the replica needs to be caught up to those so it
becomes in build we're basically saying that okay you still cannot join the replica
...because you don't have all the operation one-third has all the
operation it will become an active part of the replicas it again so,
this is...so now we have seen how we can build
a reliable stateful services using
actor programming model as well as the reliable services programming model so now
...we'll talk about well we have this word...tab
...had a single partition obviously we know that's not scalable so how do we go ahead and
scale the service, yeah, so,
the key concept of this platform is a fact that you with partitioning is first-class you
could have a scale out partitioning design and nodes and build high scale distributed applications
that can run across hundreds of machines all the time we have
...your...is left up to use a developer insiders platform we say no partitioning
is a first-class concepts and how you do your partitioning we provide different mechanism
...we...range based in sixty-four base partitioning or name
base partitioning effectively you come up with the partitioning scheme you want so you want to
use zip code is a partitioning mechanism so you want to use
...id mechanism you can easily build-out ensure choice in terms of the client
...comes in you look at some piece of information and will simply say how
...particular request...particular partitions so partitioning is just exactly you
would think in the typical concept of scaling out any application so here I segregate
my service into pieces of state and code and I...particular request
to that location without state encoded co-located and how a...across hundreds of
thousands of...so...think about this is when you build your serves you say
think about your partition requirements I might need say two thousand partitions and you can deploy
there's two thousand partitions across any number...of machines you might start off with say ten machines
and, you can grow the number machines...clusters so what does it look like typically when you deploy
inside image machines you a partitioning is deployed in one of the nodes inside the cluster of course
...replica copies across other machines annette to make it highly available
unicode deploys a second partition
...service on another machine and makes copies of that and then the third
another machine and forth so on and...pushing the partition across all these now you can
...always partitions down on to a certain number of machines and as...particular partition grows
you say simply add new machines were...the partitions out and
...accordingly...all of this is entirely transparent to-you so, for example,
say one of those partitions came particularly hot...data will say this partitions got more than
the...find a machine that's got the best
utilization of resources and...move it on to that machine so as result, you know,
this partitioning concept enables you to truly think about
high scale distributed systems ...you simply have to just understand
what you'll partitioning scheme your...concepts and we take care of striking and pushing
a partitions across the machines inside the cluster and dealing with all failures inside
of course and dealing with whether but some partitions hot compared to the others are moving them all around?
So, let's say now think...how going-to-take that same
application would application what we do instead we're going to have a
...front-end where...coming...that
...but...or load balance front-end where we have a web api we're going to look at the
...comes in and now we look at the...of that we simply going to scale-up that request
form...particular...to a particular partition we take this word...service create
...numerous partitions for it all and now when of custom from the client hit the web
...web front-end what kind of look at the request itself and send it to particular partition you
...any number of partitions usually scaled out what...declarative mechanism inside here.
...so, let's switch back again to visual studio so,
this is an application manifest this is what mark was talking...when you define
...application type you defined out in the manifest so
in this case as you can see now I have award...web service and I have a
statefull work on service my stateful...services partition
snide has thirteen partition and I have both...service as well as the statefull what
...service and in the same application so there are two service packages so you saw the slide where
...service packages and they were animated and put into the application package
well this is the application package and here are the to service packages that are defined
write a web application packet web service packet...full-service packets so,
now let's look at what does the service looks like right so in this case for the
...everything remains exactly same except that I have basically use instead of
...service communication listener so this is we
provide a communication listener out-of-the-box that you can use remember on the
on the previous case where we were using wc if I had to implement some
...I had to implement that word count service...derived
from service partition client and do bunch of work are no longer I have to do that
basically if I use service communication listener just like act-up proxy?
Create of I actor
interferes I can do service proxy create I service interface and,
I'm done I will get transparent channel to my to my service
rich actually provides location transparency so the conduct looks
exactly the same except that there are no w cf...data contract operation
conduct instead it's deriving from my service so that's one change I am made the
second...as I said...made is to basically...the web service
and change the partition cone in the web service I'm using moving communication
listener so, this is actually a...service the clients will connect to it
through...typically a rest api and
...the orrin communication listener provide stacks I'm hosting and esp
...application and creating a stateless service so this is work on
web services a stateless servicethis...a statefull partition service correct so,
now let's see how it looks like inside the clusterso,
inside the cluster as you can see I have multiple partitions I'm going to
...different view of this using what we called
a cluster monitor this is again a sample application that we
have written so both the service fabric explorer as well as this are using
over management api and this apis our public we also provide the
rest busy apis that you can you can use in order to manage or where your state
...query the cluster so I imagine that some of you will actually say hey
this service fabric exploded as gore but the
ways not that great maybe we'll build something more appealing and more pleasing to
...you can do that using the apis at the management api that we provide
...so here the same slide that mark
...you can see that there are multiple politician's so each of these black boxes represents the
node and inside that multiple applications are deployed
and within that I multiple partitions...when I...
a primary here you'll see the to two-second eddie's corresponding to that are being
...right so now let's go ahead and this term not going to do fail overall I'm going
to show you is that if a...to go down so this is node three
iphone nowhere to go down so let's go ahead and shutdown node three?
...you'll notice that we take...action and all of these primaries that are located here
...will switch and
...switch to a different node as well as all of the active secondary
...are monitors down so now that partitions that we're here the primary that where here are
still available this is the same fail over in a different visualization right so,
I'll go ahead and re enable the...
So, this is the solve healing aspect we have think about this is aac how sequel leisure runs
...of hundreds of thousands of databases machine dies...databases
...particular machine we knows exactly what was running their available over to another machine
as far as a client is concerned it's completely transparent doautomatic
...recopy allocate that...elected become a primary...that and
...no loss of service machine-made come back again will say that's available as part of the cluster again
and then starts to place new primaries...this so as far as you're concerned
machines go machines arrive and this transparent moving of these microsoft...a
...completely transparency and deals with this sort of self...system?
Let's take...questions...the end of nearly...
So, because I didn't start the work on web client I started the work on web
...and, shutdown the node again so you can see that the word
...web client is going on while the node went down the primary
fehler what happened and, then...then transparently relocated
the primary and then the work on-site continuing to happen the count across
medius partitions that are there and this is the total count across all of those partition so,
I'll go ahead and, start the node again and,
then what I'm going to do is that I'm going to
enable so in order to test your application so first of all writing stateful services
...hard you made it very simple using reliable collection but there
...still going to be certain things in your business logic that you have to take care when a
...what happens and you may...well the
fill on happen but, I'm not sure whether I'm doing the right things I want to test my service
...this a key also service this is part of the system so the key
also...starts taking action it basically restarted the
core packages it restarts replica you can see certain things happening here
...restart nodes will ensure the...is how the before moving on to the next round of the
...and...you
can continuously run this in your in your cluster and make sure nothing bad happens your clients
unhappy your clients are continuing and, you know, that your application can
...different kind of failures right so,
before we go over to somebody I would like to
our take this opportunity to thank each and every member of the service public team we've been working
hard this technology for a lot of
...as well as all of forward internal partners and consumers?
...creativity...couple of...so, you to summarize, you know,
we're pretty excited that because of the way we thought about how
...build a high scale services you we realized that when we
moved from these box products to be services you...naturally thought about how we
decomposed these books products into a concept of micros services and is very important, you know,
there's a lot of talk around contain is what they are but...don't design with containers
you design applications and applications get broken down into pieces of code and...pieces of code what
...your application and that's how we think about a microsoft...design application what it
means...fact that those micros get deployed inside...is for isolation
security is part of the characteristics you say of the requirements you want of the service I
...itself how...deployed...and we've been building this platform number of years we're very
confident in it because we know that we run it ourselves with thrilled the fact that we've given
it to you in fact the bits that we should this...I said
...being rolled out across a lot of...first...clusters and...showed you that
...very simple programming model apis
of the access side of things in a reliable something you can go away and build, you know,
stateless services like very useful giga bunches of statefull ones as well you
can compose replications of multiple pieces of code deploy them together
and application you could take existing...of new jess application or arbitrary
executables wrap them inside those service packages that we talked about and put them inside
and application package and just say hey...you to make...applications reliable
...you to deploy them I always...instances running...kill machines just make shows always
...running that's what we refer to as part of microsoft
...how we put these things together but of course if you take advantage of all runtime that we showed you today
we have deep insight into your application we can provide is health model we have
...into in fact fully encourage you to after this...can be a session I talked all about the deployment the
...and management of all this because although we show you how to develop apps here the biggest
cost by far we run one of the services...day-to-day management of these
...think about sequel leisure they've hundreds of updates today across thousands of
machines different versions that run...done...health the monitoring deep
insights what happens here all this transparently so you off this
...of a service I have a session...room next door that tells you...through the walks you through the life-cycle
...this books about how you manage
these services so have you given appreciation over this you are
...is please go and find the developer sdk download
this sdk go get the samples of...hub the...count sample and the other
sample you so here today available there ...tama...to get...started
...lots of feedback forums we want you to go...feedback format aka service fabric
form gives...feedback on the user voice this is...beginning of the journey
for us what we're going to ship the regular sdk later this year...service
inside as...only of applications that you built your...later on whether this year
we shipwindows seven twenty sixteen service fabric will be built into that you
will clusters from that deploy replications there...excited to be
...we're entering a new era of how we think about how we build these high scale
high resilient mission critical services like we run at microsoft
we've given you exactly the same technology if you to do the same and think about how we can take this
...journey of how we build to scale highly resilience services and thank you very much?
I think we have some time for some questions...please comes...microphones or
...all come up and...stage and...love to hear questions...microphones first if you want to go to...
Yeses microphone on.
Semi-final please.
Can we...the...can return the microphone please?
Do they microphones work?
Why don't you come up and then I'll repeat your question okay yes also questions and
...shout...repeated questions?
...so,...question the question is what's migration
...existing cloud services going towards this...continue to invest in cloud
...we have today the...that is cloud services will continual
...have many years as a programme...inside that will provide migration guidance
...moving forward to this effectively your seat today that the
...all model api very similar so the migration pretty much is, you know,
there's a similar program all of...provide design guidance
...our investment in cloud services you should think about this is a next generation of up has platform
...shipped this as a parallel service that you can use will keep them robo
...side-by-side ...this is one where we now have
...deployments high-density...scale and this is
...we've invested all-time so cloud sub-zero...but this is where our investment is going for?
This is your next version of our paths platform this is exactly how we
...unsaid well-run...ioc today, you know,
we showed...stateless world...you build a cloud services very...the run command
...always identically have today...a better separation of the runtime from
the environment so you can take those cloud services...applications now and run
them anyway today cloud services all sort of constrained only...as you that fixed
...locked in now you can minimum premise you can stand-up...you want to running six so you have the
benefit of run anywhere fast deployment high-density this is the next generation of that.
...is how they fit with resource manager you'll see that will stand-up a service
later this year that has a resource manager definition of the next
organ they'll talk about all actually that's even better in the next...that follows
will show you exactly how you...a cluster will show you the portal what runs like a defined
resource manager template but yes...have a template definition of...a cluster machines and
...applications...one question here,...
Yeah, so, you can actually question so it's
...question all the question is what happens if I actually
...down-and-out cluster and...restart...the data is...stored on the disk and
...if you shut down the cluster as long as you're hardest...bottom or
...available you will be able to recover from read where you...
...to know...google there is no...started backing this is the store your local hard disk is
the store you can however for disaster recovery as well as so, for example,
for disaster where to happen and you say
while the entire ragged one down and I didn't actually you look at the
...you could...or dot is a different
frequency it's accorded data that's only for disaster the ability to not in your
heart application odp odf enhancer latency...I'm not going to be affected by
...general design that we've come across here where you hold...tiered made highly...scalable and
...might be the last-minute lost our last day and then you can offload that data to
back and as you...result you have this very low latency high throughput systems you built...for example,
you could...think about it hundreds and hundreds of request coming the second evaluate they tried to
...with storage and put all these event that they would be...the
...io t like the perfect example of this sort of system it systems
wave huge amounts of incoming data we want to run rules on it all, yeah,
that's what...equalizer bills like this...the database is stored on local
disks inside the...db...stored on local this from machines in...hubs as
...event hubs, you know,...we take advantage of using the same mechanism.
Next expression yes I actually while we were talking I actually shut
down the local cluster that is there are no...so I for...all of the nodes I'm going to restarted again
well we while we take...expression you can you can go back from...
Which this?
Okay, so,
the question is you I have my actually db running and I have a client connection to a particular a
primary is running...so,...client when the client
...back in again we have a naming service that is revisit...of where the chron
pr primary is...so it all think of it as a service that...like dns for the whole
cluster when something fails over everything every much service has a unique name, you know, this is
move from here to here...comes back in again the naming services like...the cluster goes always
...so we redirect the client whether you primaries and all that just happens transparency.
Well, once you've established to a primary that it is a tcb connections...yes but if you lose that will
re-establish connection again...but and how it does that it goes in and ask service fabric
...when you primary...or it is active and it just reconnected in...machine again and that's what you
...wrapped up in...apis at service partition resolve that automatic
...resolution...discovery for-you in terms of where things off so things move around the
whole time things fail things...it doesn't...find it for you?
...we provide out-of-the-box communication protocols post on
web api...if you want to build your own one based on tcp sockets ftp
...and caving this implementers small piece of I communication list
...your own one so we don't really go...the community provide
...out-of-the-box communication...to talk...microsoft's...going to build
...talking create go ahead it's free most about benefit is in fact dealing with
failed over discovery lifecycle management and,
resilience and, composition of a service into small pieces of code.
Intuitive...on this is about transactions across the...so the
...that we...timeout...so if you have a big thing inside your transaction
it's going on the other guy is going...and say I cannot...the law for this particular
key and...or if they are not conflicting both of them will go in...and,
the transactions that you so you also different other question which is what happens if I
have a large set of items inside the transaction what happens is that as
you're making the changes those are actually getting replicated at that point in time to
...not waiting for the commit what assuming that most of the commits will successful enhance
we can actually...you're doing it so as a result we don't accumulate a large
be chunk and then replicate in the and it's actually replicating so
...not accumulating that.
Yes.
While for enumeration it is multi version so it is...for the enumeration it...multi
...isolation.
Yeah, because if you...repeatable...you'll get phantom...in when you do the enumeration in order to
...vehement diversion for...
Yes, or no...online...yes...riyadh...online this is the next question were pretty good time for a couple.
No, it was it was it was all running on this machine
and in fact you if you notice I wasn't even connected anywhere on the wireless and
...you can actually so in a production that particular
...will be one node on one machine but, you can actually configure two-run
multiple nodes within within the same machine in fact in...cast we
...hundreds of ignored not only on same machine but within the same process so we're able to
do lot...and actually...white box testing to be able to figure outso,
the court is exactly the same there is no difference in terms
of whether it is running on a single box with ten nodes or whether it's running
inside the jd with one more than one and,...for those who
...mike mongers on...demo yesterday...voting...we actually had a
hundreds of machines that running in the background he didn't show the hundreds of machines but we had
...piling hundreds of...into a set of services we were running to show you the...
on any just partitioned out the application across a of many machines your choice.
what happens is that the cluster without monitored in one of the slide that the nodes are forming the
clustered so let's say if you had one machine go down we will detect
that machine is down and the rest of the nor will basically hilo rounded and
form the cluster and then feel over the workload that was on this machine to a different,
different machine in this give the entire cluster...because I
have all the nodes in the cluster on the same machine...dinner told this happening next within
...clusters running on as you were going to use that same attacking the
eyesore accessibility service to actually showed accessibility of clusters running...as you're not just on
your local machine so you'll see that and if you notice I think this is a
little bit more deeper but if you notice I did something else as well before starting...what we call
...files that's basically to prevent...situation so it I knew that I have the entire
cluster down if I had only the portion of the
cluster down or there was a network partition...there is a
...duration for which we will...before we'll say those machines are dead and those machines will
actually go down those nodes will actually go down to you will never health split
between situation in your cluster...technologies very important in building a platform?
Yes, so, the...available everything you see runs on your local
...box just as and then what happens is you'll simply go up to either
...say creamy?
...ten machine vm cluster of this running then the option just
...in exactly the same way you saw running here in the same when from
...you can...them all is like...
All-you-can-eat...yeah, we run it all on...
Correct so we're question is it on premise yes you'll see a few months triangle
...version of you can create a cluster insight asher of machines we
...part of windows have a twenty sixteen so you've got to take windows server you will network
them all together turn on service...fun have...cluster anyway, you have
...network connectives you can build a cluster of machines effectively.
This technology moi.
...so, there are multiple layers of the apis...talk.
Locate...why don't we go out...think the question.